Matthew Ellenberger papers, Inclusive: 1798-1983, Bulk: 1836-1975
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Matthew Ellenberger papers
Inclusive: 1798-1983, Bulk: 1836-1975
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
2703
Ellenberger, Matthew
1 document box.
The Matthew Ellenberger papers contain Ellenberger’s research notes and correspondence as well as literary publications concerning Albert C. Horton, Thomas Walker, and Jack Jouett.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Matthew Ellenberger was born in San Antonio, Texas, and was educated at the Universities of Tennessee and Oregon. As of 1985 he was living in Annapolis, Maryland. Ellenberger wrote articles on obscure figures in American history, especially those connected with early movements for independence and settlement. The materials in this collection concern Albert Clinton Horton, Thomas Walker, and Jack Jouett.
Albert Clinton Horton (1798-1865) served as a representative in the Alabama State Legislature before moving to Texas in 1835. In the Texas Revolution, he became a colonel, and was responsible for gathering many volunteers. In 1836 he attempted to rescue Colonel James Fannin at Goliad, but was repelled by the Mexicans and forced to retreat. This action made Horton a controversial figure in his time, but even so, he continued to advance in his career, eventually becoming one of the wealthiest men in Texas. He was elected the first lieutenant governor of Texas, and was a charter member of Baylor University’s Board of Trustees.
Dr. Thomas Walker (1714-1794) was a wealthy Virginian and a prominent physician in the years before the American Revolution. He was a member of the House of Burgesses in multiple counties, and performed various other civil duties. He was also appointed the guardian of the young Thomas Jefferson. His most notable accomplishment, though, was his role in exploring Kentucky and aiding in opening its frontiers for settlement.
Jack Jouett (1754-1822), from Virginia, was a Captain in the American Revolution. In 1781 he discovered a plot by the British general Lord Cornwallis to send Lieutenant Colonel Banastre Tarleton to capture several key leaders in the Revolution, including Thomas Jefferson, Patrick Henry, Benjamin Harrison, and Richard Henry Lee, who were then in an assembly in Charlottesville, Virginia. Jouett rode forty miles through the woods, in the dark, to warn his defenseless compatriotsDLan act that likely saved the Revolution. In his later years, he went to Kentucky and helped it gain its independence and to prepare the way for settlers.
Scope and Content
The Matthew Ellenberger papers consist of items compiled by Ellenberger for his own research. They contain a number of articles about Albert Clinton Horton, correspondence between Ellenberger and the sources of his information, and his research notes. There are a few extensive literary publications concerning Thomas Walker as well as some shorter articles, and also a couple of articles about Jack Jouett.
Arrangement
Currently the Matthew Ellenberger papers are arranged in three series: I. Albert C. Horton, II. Thomas Walker, III. Jack Jouett.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 2703. Acquired 1985-11-21
Related Resources
Related references
Dabney, Virginius. “Jack Jouett’s Ride.” American Heritage. Volume 13, Issue 1. December 1961.
Ellenberger, Matthew. “Illuminating the Lesser Lights: Notes on the Life of Albert Clinton Horton.”.
Zontine, Patricia. “Dr. Thomas Walker.”.
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Horton, Albert Clinton, 1798-1865.; Jouett, Jack, 1754-1822.
Genres
Correspondence.; Essays.; Research notes.
- Albert C. Horton, 1798-1983; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series consists of Matthew Ellenberger’s notes taken during his research of Albert Clinton Horton, correspondence between Ellenberger and the sources of his information, and literary productions such as articles and encyclopedic entries about Horton. These materials are in good condition.
  - Research Notes: (1 of 2), 1830-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Research Notes: (2 of 2), 1830-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Research Notes, 1798-1966 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence: (1 of 2), 1836-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence: (2 of 2), 1836-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Literary Publications: (1 of 3), 1836-1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Literary Publications: (2 of 3), 1836-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Literary Publications: (3 of 3), 1836-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Thomas Walker, 1931-1979; 2
  This series consists of literary publications, including a thesis, research paper, Antiquarian Society report, encyclopedic entries, journal, and articles of Thomas Walker. These materials are in good condition.
  - Literary Publications, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Literary Publications (1 of 2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Literary Publications (2 of 2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Literary Publications, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Literary Publications, 1975; undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Jack Jouett, 1928, 1981; 3
  This series consists of a couple of articles about Jack Jouett used for Ellenberger’s research. This series is in good condition.
  - Literary Publications: Articles, 1928; 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)